Stephen Crane Collection
Stephen Crane Collection
- Lillian Gilkes research files
  - Writings
    - Articles
      - "More on 'How Crane Got to Greece': a Moot Question", 1972; typescript ms. (Box 9)
      - "Not at Columbia: Postcards to Cora Crane" / Lillian Gilkes and Joseph Katz Columbia Library Columns, Feb. 1974 (Box 9)
      - "Stephen and Cora Crane: Some Corrections, and a 'Millionaire' Named Sharefe", typescript ms. (Box 9)
      - "Stephen Crane and the Biographical Fallacy: The Cora Influence" - Modern Fiction Studies, Winter 1970-71; typescripts and a reprint (Box 9)
      - "The Stephen Crane Collection Before Its Acquisition by Columbia: a Memoir" Columbia Library Columns, Nov. 1973 (Box 9)
      - "Stephen Crane, John Hay, and Dr. Nathan E. Boyd", typescript with corrections (Box 9)
      - "Stephen Crane's Burial Place: Some Inconsequential Ghost Laying", typescript (Box 9)
    - Book reviews
      - "Corrections of R.W. Stallman's Stephen Crane: a Biography" - Stephen Crane Newsletter, Spring 1969 (Box 9)
      - "A Recent Book About Stephen Crane", review of Stephen Crane: a Biography / R.W. Stallman - The Courier, Spring 1969; typescript, author's proofs (Box 9)
      - "Some Omissions" - Saturday Review, Aug. 31, 1968 (Box 9)
      - Stephen Crane / John Berryman, unpublished typescript (Box 9)
      - "Stephen Crane: Ecrivain-journaliste, 1871-1900" (1969) / Jean Cazemajou American Literature, Jan. 1971 (Box 9)
    - Books
      - Cora Crane: a Biography of Mrs. Stephen Crane
        - Typescript ms., 3 folders (Box 9)
        - Production records, author's proof with corrections (Box 10)
        - Production records, cover design, advertising pamphlet, illustrations list (Box 10)
      - Stephen Crane: Letters / R.W. Stallman and Lillian Gilkes, editors, 1960; production records - advertisements (Box 10)
    - Miscellany (Box 10)
  - Memorabilia
    - Photographs
      - "The Luncheon given by the Society of American Women in London, Victoria Hall, Hotel Cecil, London", July 3rd, 1899; 1 mounted original and 1 copy (Oversize 1)
      - Negatives, miscellaneous (Box 10)
      - Photographs, miscellaneous (Box 10)
    - Printed material
      - Clippings, miscellaneous (Box 10)
    - Writings by others
      - Experiment in Autobiography / H.G. Wells -, typescript passage from book (Box 10)
      - "George Gissing on Frederic: a Correction" / Robert H. Woodward - The Frederic Herald, Jan. 1969 (Box 10)
      - "How Stephen Crane Got to Crete" / R.W. Stallman - American Literature, undated (Box 10)
      - "Jacksonville's Most Famous Madam" / Peggy Friedman - Jacksonville, May/June 1980 (Box 10)
      - Joseph Conrad and His Circle / Jessie Conrad, 1935; typescript notes from book (Box 10)
      - More Lives Than One / Claude Bragdon, excerpts (Box 10)
      - "Stallman's Crane" / Thomas A. Gullason - The CEA Critic, May 1969 (Box 10)
      - "Stephen Crane - a Biography by R.W. Stallman" American Literature, May 1969; publicity (Box 10)
    - Miscellany
      - Brass button given by Cora Taylor (Crane) to Henry W. Walters (Box 10)
      - Calling cards of Cora Crane and her companion, Mrs. Ruedy (Box 10)
- Cyrus Day research files
  - Correspondence, 1957-1962; concerning the Jan 3, 1897 wreck of the ship Commodore (Box 11)
  - Notes on the Commodore wreck and Stephen Crane (Box 11)
  - Memorabilia
    - Clippings of articles (copies) about the Commodore wreck, some by Stephen Crane, Jan. 3, 1897-Jan. 7, 1897 (Box 11)
    - Photographs and illustrations related to the Commodore wreck, Stephen Crane, and correspondents in Florida during the Spanish-American War (Box 11)
- Mansfield J. French research files
  - Correspondence
    - Esmond, Burton D., 1930 (Box 11)
    - Lafayette College, 1930 (Box 11)
    - Robinson, Christian, 1932 (Box 11)
    - Schoberlin, Melvin H., 1947-1948 (Box 11)
    - Travis, A. Lincoln, 1930 (Box 11)
  - Writings
    - "Stephen Crane, Ball Player", holograph (Box 11)
- Frank W. Noxon research files
  Files consist entirely of correspondence.
  - Esmond, Burton D., 1930 (Box 11)
  - French, M. J., 1934 (Box 11)
  - Herzberg, Max J., 1926-1927 (Box 11)
  - Linson, Corwin Knapp, 1930 (Box 11)
  - Perry, William H., 1926 (Box 11)
  - Robinson, Christian, 1931 (Box 11)
  - Taber, Harry P., 1929 (Box 11)
- Vincent Starrett research files
  - Bacheller, Irving, 1927 (Box 11)
  - Cary, Henry N., 1922 (Box 11)
  - Conrad, Joseph, 1919; undated (Box 11)
  - Dulau and Company, Ltd., 1927 (Box 11)
  - Emerson, Edwin, 1928 (Box 11)
  - Esmond, Burton, 1930 (Box 11)
  - Frewen, Moreton, 1922 (Box 11)
  - Harriman, Karl E., 1934 (Box 11)
  - Linson, Corwin Knapp, 1931 (Box 11)
  - Mayfield, John S., 1943 (Box 11)
  - Somerville, Peter F., 1928-1933 (Box 11)
  - Vielbe-Griffin, Francis, 1929 (Box 11)
  - A-Z (miscellaneous) (Box 11)
- Corwin Knapp Linson writings
  - My Stephen Crane, third revision (working title: "Stephen Crane Memories and Appreciation"), holograph (Box 12)
  - My Stephen Crane, third revision (working title: "Stephen Crane Memories and Appreciation), holograph manuscript, bound (Box 12)
  - My Stephen Crane (working title: "Stephen Crane A Personal Record), typescript, includes photos and death certificate (Box 12)
  - My Stephen Crane, typescript photocopy, pp. 1-88; 2 folders (Box 12)
  - My Stephen Crane, printer's typescript copy, 1958 (Box 12)
- Melvin H. Schoberlin research files
  - Correspondence-subject files
    - A (Box 13)
    - Abramson, Ben, 1949-1950 (Box 13)
    - Adams, George Matthew, 1946-1950 (Box 13)
    - Allen, Francis H., 1941 (Box 13)
    - Allen, Frederick L., 1941 (Box 13)
    - Allen, Gardner Weld, 1941 (Box 13)
    - B (Box 13)
    - Barrett, Clifton Waller, 1958-1968 (Box 13)
    - Beer, Alice, 1948-1956 (Box 13)
    - Beer, Thomas (Box 13)
      See also Beer, Alice; Herzberg, Max J.; Starrett, Vincent.
    - Bowers, Fredson, 1967-1974 (Box 13)
    - Bruccoli, Matthew J., 1966-1971 (Box 13)
    - Lucius L. Button Family, 1948 (Box 13)
    - C (Box 13)
    - Clemens, Cyril, 1947-1949 (Box 13)
    - Collamore, H. B., 1946-1950 (Box 13)
    - Crane, Edith and Crane Family, 1922-1962 (Box 13)
    - Nellie Crouse Family, 1948 (Box 13)
    - D (Box 13)
    - E (Box 13)
    - Edel, Leon, 1948-1949 (Box 13)
    - F (Box 13)
    - Fretwell, Elizabeth and Mark, 1947-1948 (Box 13)
    - G (Box 13)
    - Ghodes, Clarence, 1951 (Box 14)
    - Gibson, Donald B., 1967 (Box 14)
    - Gilkes, Lillian, 1954-1973; undated (Box 14)
    - Goodwin, Clarence N., 1948-1949 (Box 14)
    - Greene, Nelson, 1944-1949 (Box 14)
    - H (Box 14)
    - Hathaway, Odell, 1948-1950 (Box 14)
    - Herzberg, Max J., 1936-1949 (Box 14)
    - I (Box 14)
    - K (Box 14)
    - Katz, Joseph, 1963-1970 (Box 14)
    - Alfred A. Knopf Incorporated, 1946-1950 (Box 14)
    - L (Box 14)
    - Lawrence, Frederic M., 1948-1949 (Box 14)
    - Linson, Corwin Knapp, 1946-1954 (Box 14)
    - M (Box 14)
    - N (Box 14)
    - Norris, Kathleen Thompson, 1948 (Box 14)
    - O (Box 14)
    - P (Box 14)
    - Pease, Michael and Nicolas, 1948-1955 (Box 14)
    - R (Box 15)
    - Rosenbach Company, 1946-1948 (Box 15)
    - S (Box 15)
    - Lewis Senger Family, 1948-1949 (Box 15)
    - Snyder, Edgar C., 1949-1952 (Box 15)
    - Stallman, Robert Wooster, 1951-1957 (Box 15)
    - Starrett, Vincent, 1922-1948 (Box 15)
    - Syracuse University Press, 1948-1968 (Box 15)
    - T (Box 15)
    - U (Box 15)
    - V (Box 15)
    - W (Box 15)
    - Wheeler, Post, 1947-1952 (Box 15)
    - Williams, Ames W., 1946-1950 (Box 15)
    - Y (Box 15)
  - Writings
    - Books
      - Flagon of Despair (unpublished)
        - Book proposal, Guggenheim Fellowship application (Box 15)
        - Master copy (Book I, 167pp; Book II 159pp; Book III 130 pp.), 3 folders (Box 15)
        - "Original rough" [draft], 2 folders (Box 16)
        - "Copy II", 2 folders (Box 16)
        - Chapter XI (Box 16)
        - Chapter XV - draft and notes (Box 16)
        - Criticisms and suggestions (Box 17)
        - Notes (Box 17)
        - Production records - cover ideas, preface (Box 17)
        - Production records - photographs, 3 folders (Box 17)
      - From Candles to Footlights, production records - advertisements (Box 17)
      - Sullivan County Sketches of Stephen Crane, production records - book covers, advertisements, illustration work (Box 17)
    - Notes
      - America 1800-1900 (Box 17)
      - Bibliographies of Crane material (Box 17)
      - Bohnenberger, Carl - inventory of Crane material (Box 18)
      - Book dealers (Box 18)
      - Brandon, Lily (Mrs. Smillie), 1895-1949 (Box 18)
      - Chronological Crane history index, See Indexes: Index file #3 (Box 25)
      - Colour notebook (Box 18)
      - Conrad, Joseph - letters to and about S. Crane (copies) (Box 18)
      - Copeland and Day publications checklist, 1893-1899 (Box 18)
      - Crane, Agnes - writings (Box 18)
      - Crane, Cora, background, America (Box 18)
      - Crane, Cora, background, England (Box 18)
      - Cora Crane correspondence, 1897-1910; copies (Box 18)
      - Cora Crane writings, 1901; copies (Box 18)
      - Crane, Jonathan Townley, writings (copies) (Box 18)
      - Crane, Mary Helen, writings (copies) (Box 18)
      - Crane, Stephen
        - Background, 1871-1898; 25 folders (Box 19)
        - Background, 1899-1900; 2 folders (Box 20)
        - Biographical materials (Box 20)
        - Correspondence, incoming (copies), 1893-1900; undated (Box 20)
        - Correspondence, outgoing, 1886-1900; undated; copies; 3 folders (Box 20)
        - Crouse, Nellie, 1895-1896; correspondence (typescript copies) (Box 20)
        - Eulogies (Box 20)
        - Genealogy (Box 20)
        - Legends (Box 20)
        - Letters about Crane, 1896-1930; undated; copies (Box 20)
        - Newark, N.J. tablet dedication, 1921 (Box 20)
        - Portraits and postage stamp design (Box 20)
        - Writings
          - Chronology (Box 20)
          - Criticism and background
            - Active Service (Box 20)
            - The Black Riders (Box 20)
            - "Blood of the Martyr" (Box 20)
            - Dan Emmonds (Box 20)
            - George's Mother (Box 20)
            - Great Battles of the World (Box 20)
            - Last Words (Box 21)
            - The Little Regiment (Box 21)
            - Maggie (Box 21)
            - Men, Women, and Boats (Box 21)
            - The Monster (Box 21)
            - "Ol' Bennet & the Indians" (Box 21)
            - The Open Boat (Box 21)
            - The O'Ruddy (Box 21)
            - The Red Badge of Courage (Box 21)
            - The Third Violet (Box 21)
            - War is Kind (Box 21)
            - Whilomville Stories (Box 21)
            - Wounds in the Rain (Box 21)
          - Criticism by Crane (Box 21)
          - Greek-Turkish War, 1897 (Box 21)
          - Philosophy of Crane (Box 21)
          - Press articles, 1894-1900 (Box 21)
          - Spanish American War, 1898; undated (Box 21)
          - Views on literature (Box 21)
          - Miscellany, 1880-1898 (Box 21)
            See also Index file #3 and Index file #4 in Box 25)
      - Crane contemporaries, American (Box 21)
      - Crane contemporaries, British (Box 22)
      - Criticism of Crane, general (Box 22)
      - Cuba War and background (Box 22)
      - Frederic, Harold (Box 22)
      - Garland, Hamlin (Box 22)
      - Hawkins, Willis B., See Leslie, Amy / Hawkins, Willis B.
      - Herzberg, Max, correspondence about Crane (Box 22)
      - Index, Chronological Crane history, See Indexes: Index file #3 (Box 25)
      - Index, Name - Researchers, Sources, Crane contemporaries, See Indexes: Index file #2 (Box 25)
      - Index, Original Manuscripts, See Indexes: Index file #3 (Box 25)
      - Index, Periodicals, See Indexes: Index file #1 (Box 25)
      - Index, Writings by or about Crane, noting published locations and Schoberlin's sources; See Indexes: Index file #3 and Index file #4 (Box 25)
      - Legal papers, Crane (Box 22)
      - Leslie, Amy / Hawkins, Willis B., 1896-1897; correspondence (copies) (Box 22)
      - Leslie, Amy / Hawkins, Willis B., 1896-1926; clippings (Oversize 2)
      - Little magazines (Box 22)
        See also Indexes: Index file #1 (Box 25)
      - Parodies of Crane (Box 22)
      - Peck, George, 1860; writings (Box 22)
      - Peck, Harry Thurston, writings (Box 23)
      - U.S. Marine Corps, correspondence about Crane (Box 23)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 23)
  - Memorabilia
    - Printed material
      - Book, Asbury Park Directory, 1885 (Box 23)
      - Clippings
        - About Stephen Crane, 1896-1948 (Box 23)
        - Asbury Park newspapers, 1879; 1886 (Oversize 2)
        - From Candles to Footlights / M. Schoberlin, reviews and notices (Box 23)
        - Stephen Crane articles, 1891-1900 (Box 23)
        - Stephen Crane articles, 1892-1900; copies (Oversize 2)
        - Sullivan County Sketches / Schoberlin, M., ed., reviews (Box 23)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 23)
    - Photographs and illustrations
      - Brede Place (Box 23)
      - Crane, Cora, 1892 (Box 23)
      - Crane, Stephen
        - British locations Crane may have visited (Box 23)
        - Portraits (copy photographs and negatives, illustrations, caricatures) (Box 23)
          See also Oversize package 2
        - U.S. locations Crane may have visited (Box 23)
        - Writings (photographs and negatives) (Box 23)
      - Cranes' (Stephen and Cora) grave sites (Box 23)
      - Pennsylvania and Lafayette College (Box 23)
      - Schoberlin, Melvin, portraits (Box 23)
      - Miscellaneous oversize (Oversize 2)
    - Writings by others
      - "Mr. Stephen Crane: an Appreciation" / Edward Garnett (Box 23)
      - "The Red Badge of Courage and the Civil War tradition in Fiction: 1861-1895" / Joseph Ridgely, 1947 (Box 23)
      - "Stephen Crane and His Work" / Edward Garnett (Box 23)
      - "Stephen Crane's Revisions of Maggie: a Girl of the Streets" / Robert Wooster Stallman, 1955 (Box 23)
      - "Study of the Criticisms on Stephen Crane" / Benedict Wolf, 1928 (Box 23)
    - Miscellany
      - Crane, Cora - spanish moss from above her grave (Box 23)
      - Stationery sheet with heading, "Crane's New Jersey Coast News Bureau, Sandy Hook to Barnegat Bay, Asbury Park, N.J. Townley Crane, Manager, Stephen Crane, Secretary, Edgar C. Snyder, Treasurer", 1891-1892 (Box 23)
  - Indexes
    - Index File #1 - Periodicals (Box 25)
    - Index File #2 - Researchers, sources, Crane contemporaries (Box 25)
    - Index File #3 - Original manuscripts; Chronological Crane history; Writings by or about Crane (Box 25)
    - Index File #4 - Writings by or about Crane; Miscellany (Box 25)
- Ames Williams research files
  - Correspondence-subject files
    - Arms, George, 1944 (Box 24)
    - B (Box 24)
    - Bacheller, Irving, 1941 (Box 24)
    - Boston Public Library, 1942 (Box 24)
    - British Museum, 1942 (Box 24)
    - Collamore, H. B., 1941-1942 (Box 24)
    - Crane, Cora / Pinker, J. - typescript copies of corresp. (Box 24)
    - Crane, S. / Pinker, J. - typescript copies of corresp. (Box 24)
    - Crane, S. / Reynolds, P. R. - typescript copies of corresp. (Box 24)
    - D, 1942 (Box 24)
    - E, 1955 (Box 24)
    - French, Mansfield, 1934-1951 (Box 24)
    - Funk & Wagnalls Company, 1941 (Box 24)
    - G, 1940-1942 (Box 24)
    - Gaines, Charles Kelsey, 1942 (Box 24)
    - H, 1942 (Box 24)
    - Harper Brothers, 1942 (Box 24)
    - Hearst, William Randolph, 1941 (Box 24)
    - William Heinemann, Ltd., 1942-1945 (Box 24)
    - Hill, Eldon, 1942 (Box 24)
    - J, 1941-1945 (Box 24)
    - L, 1941-1942 (Box 24)
    - Linson, Corwin Knapp, 1941-1944 (Box 24)
    - Little, Charles G., 1941 (Box 24)
    - M, 1941 (Box 24)
    - Mason, A. E. W., 1946 (Box 24)
    - Mott, Howard, 1943 (Box 24)
    - N, 1941-1942 (Box 24)
    - P, 1941-1942 (Box 24)
    - Pinker, James, See Crane, Cora / Pinker, James and Crane, Stephen / Pinker, James (Box 24)
    - R, 1941-1942 (Box 24)
    - Reynolds, Paul Revere, See Crane, S. / Reynolds, P. R. (Box 24)
    - S, 1941-1942 (Box 24)
    - Sheridan, Clare, 1945 (Box 24)
    - Syracuse University, 1941-1961 (Box 24)
    - T, 1941 (Box 24)
    - U, 1941-1942 (Box 24)
    - W, 1941-1945 (Box 24)
    - Wheeler, Post, 1942 (Box 24)
  - Writings
    - "Alexandria, Virginia, Christmas 1954", Mar. 26, 1961; private printing of Stephen Crane article "Fire!" with description by Ames Williams (Box 24)
    - "On Collecting Stephen Crane", Mar. 26, 1961; typescript of paper presented before the Manuscript Society (Box 24)
  - Memorabilia
    - Photograph, Lily Brandon, copy photo (Box 24)
- Recordings
  - Charles Kuralt interview with Prof. Walter Sutton in CBS series: Exploring America - discussion of Stephen Crane, Thanksgiving week, 1979; crane_s_002; Written on the back of the box: "Not for broadcast purposes".; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 26)
  - A Conversation Between Linda Davis and John Conway - Stephen Crane, crane_s_004; Note on the back of the cassette case: "Produced by the Sullivan County Historical Society, this 30 minute video is a conversation between Linda Davis, author of Badge of Courage, A Biography of Stephen Crene, and Sullivan Historian John Conway. Together they explore the writings and life of Stephen Crane.; 1/2 inch videotape; running time 30:00 (Box 26)
  - Program by Virginia Wren, with guest: Lillian Gilkes, author of Cora Crane and co-author of Stephen Crane, Letters, crane_s_001; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 26)
  - The Readers’ Almanac: guest Lillian Gilkes, author of Cora Crane, Nov. 1, 1960; crane_s_003; Note on the back of the box reads: "Not continuity, intro and Interview only". Copy of the label is in the box.; 1/4 inch audio tape; running time 23:26 (Box 26)
  - SU Library Associates Lecture - Stephen Crane: One Biographer's Journey by Linda Davis, 9/9/99; crane_s_005; 1/2 inch videotape (Box 26)